Lillian Reiner Collection
Lillian Reiner Collection
1890-1991
Reiner, Lillian
12 linear ft.
Spanning 1890 to 1991, the Lillian Reiner Collection comprises Correspondence/subject files, Writings, and Memorabilia relating to the Syracuse, New York teacher and political activist (1901-1987).
2524844
Biographical History
Lillian Reiner (1901-1987) was a native of Syracuse, New York and a civil rights and peace activist. She graduated from Syracuse University at the age of 64 and ran unsuccessfully for mayor, State Legislature, Congress and other offices as a member of the Onondaga County Liberal Party. In her campaigns, she often drew attention to issues of human services and the threat of nuclear weapons.
She was a member of the National Council of Negro Women, the National Organization for Women, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People and the American Civil Liberties Union. She was an advocate of gay rights and belonged to a number of peace organizatons, including the Syracuse Peace Council.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
A perpetual candidate and letter writer, Lillian Reiner was an active voice in many liberal causes and her interests and activism provide a unique perspective on the political climate of Central New York in the second half of the Twentieth Century. The Lillian Reiner Collection comprises Correspondence/subject files, Writings, and Memorabilia relating to the Syracuse, New York teacher and political activist (1901-1987).
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence/subject files (Boxes 1-3) illustrate the wide range of issues and organizations to which Reiner gave her time and talent, as well as her many campaigns for political office.
Including articles, letters to editors, and class notes by Lillian Reiner, Writings (Box 4) primarily comprise material gathered for Gutsy Lady, Reiner’s memoir, which was completed by Sari Biklen, Janet Bogdan, Karen DeCrow, and Jean M. Hoefer following Reiner’s death.
Memorabilia (Boxes 5-8) includes clippings, photographs, and printed material as well as Reiner’s collection of political buttons.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Activism and social reform; Reiner, Lillian, Archives; Liberal Party of New York State; Women political activists, New York (State); Women political candidates, New York (State); Women social reformers; Sociology; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Notes (documents); Photographs.; Social reformers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Sari Biklen, Janet Bogdan, Karen DeCrow, and Jean M. Hoefer. Refer to donor file or finding aids file for itemized donor/material list.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - General correspondence (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence (Box 1)
    See also Brooks, Rodney A. and Elman, Isadore
  - Abortion rights (Box 1)
  - Abzug, Bella S. (Box 1)
  - Action Coalition to Create Opportunities for Retirement with Dignity, Inc. (Box 1)
  - Adams, Sherman A. (Box 1)
  - Advocates Dedicated to Vigorous Ongoing Change of Attitudes Toward the Elderly (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Women, Syracuse Branch (Box 1)
  - American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born (Box 1)
  - American Jewish Congress (Box 1)
  - American Labor Party (Box 1)
  - American–Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (Box 1)
  - Americans for Democratic Action (Box 1)
  - Auer, Martin S. (Box 1)
  - Biklen, Sari (Box 1)
  - Black civil rights (Box 1)
  - Brooks, Rodney A. (Box 1)
  - Campaigns
    - 1954 - U.S. Representative, 35th Congressional District (Box 1)
    - 1973 - Mayor of Syracuse (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1974 - New York State Assembly, 121st District (Box 1)
    - 1976 - U.S. Representative, 33rd Congressional District (Box 1)
    - 1977 - Onondaga County Clerk (Box 1)
    - 1978 - U.S. Representative, 32nd Congressional District (Box 1)
    - 1982 - New York State Assembly, 120th District (Box 1)
    - 1983 - Onondaga County Executive (Box 1)
    - 1987 - Onondaga County Executive (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - Canadian Aid for Vietnam Civilians (Vancouver, BC) (Box 1)
  - Central New York Committee Against Racism and Apartheid (Box 1)
  - Children’s Center of Brookline and Greater Boston, The (Box 1)
  - Children’s Television Workshop (New York, NY) (Box 1)
  - Citizens for Water (Syracuse, NY) (Box 1)
  - Citizens United Against Police Brutality (Syracuse, NY) (Box 1)
  - Community Action Group Concerned with the Needs of the Institutionalized Elderly (Box 1)
  - Congress of Racial Equality (Box 1)
  - Consumer Information Service Center, Syracuse, NY (Box 1)
  - Cousins, Norman (Box 1)
  - Cowen, June C. (Box 1)
  - DeBenedittis, Victor (Box 1)
  - DeCrow, Karen (Box 1)
  - Eastern Airlines (Box 1)
  - Education (Box 1)
  - Elderhostel (Box 1)
  - Elman, Isadore (Box 1)
  - Equal Rights Amendment (Box 1)
  - Feiner, Irving, See Young Progressives of America, Syracuse University Chapter
  - Fisher, Marguerite J. (Box 1)
  - Foster Grandparent Program (Box 1)
  - Frontiers in Elementary Education Conference, July 14-16, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Gay rights (Box 1)
  - General Electric (Box 1)
  - Gray Panthers (Box 1)
  - The Guardian (Box 1)
  - Harambee, Inc., See Westcott Youth Organization (Syracuse, NY)
  - Hanley, James M. (Box 1)
  - Housing, Syracuse, NY, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Hunt, James B. (Box 1)
  - Hyman, Irwin I. (Box 1)
  - Javits, Jacob K. (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Edwin Carl (Box 1)
  - Krupsak, May Ann (Box 1)
  - League of Women Shoppers, Inc. (Box 1)
  - League of Women Voters (Box 1)
  - Liberal Party of New York State (Box 1)
  - Lytell, Elaine (Box 1)
  - Manwell, Elizabeth M. (Box 1)
  - Marcantonio, Vito (Box 1)
  - May Memorial Unitarian Society (Syracuse, NY) (Box 2)
  - McMahon, Brien (Box 2)
  - Meadowbrook Area Task Force (Syracuse, NY) (Box 2)
  - Meals on Wheels (Box 2)
  - Migrant labor (Box 2)
  - Military draft (Box 2)
  - Municipal power (Box 2)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (Box 2)
  - National Committee to Reopen the Rosenberg Case, See Rosenberg/Sobell case
  - National Committee to Secure Justice for Morton Sobell, See Rosenberg/Sobell case
  - National Committee to Secure Justice in the Rosenberg Case, See Rosenberg/Sobell case
  - National Committee to Secure Justice in the Rosenberg-Sobell Case, See Rosenberg/Sobell case
  - National Council of American-Soviet Friendship (Box 2)
  - National Council of Senior Citizens, Inc. (Box 2)
  - National Council of Jewish Women (Box 2)
  - National Council of Negro Women (Box 2)
  - National Emergency Civil Liberties Committee (Box 2)
  - National Labor Committee for Clemency for the Rosenbergs, See Rosenberg/Sobell case
  - National Organization for Women, 1968-1987; undated; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - National Small Business Association (Box 2)
  - National Women’s Political Caucus (Box 2)
  - New Jewish Agenda (Box 2)
  - New York Civil Liberties Union, Central New York Chapter (Box 2)
  - New York State Assembly (Box 2)
  - New York State Senate, Standing Committee on Labor (Box 2)
  - New York State Teachers’ Retirement System (Box 2)
  - New York State Women’s Political Caucus, See National Women’s Political Caucus
  - New York State Workmen’s Compensation Board (Box 2)
  - Nuclear arms (Box 2)
  - Nuclear power (Box 2)
  - On the Rise Bakery (Syracuse, NY) (Box 2)
  - Onondaga County Women’s Political Caucus, See National Women’s Political Caucus
  - Onondaga Independent Citizens’ Committee, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Pageant (Box 2)
  - Peace Now Jerusalem (Box 2)
  - Peacewriters Network (Box 2)
  - Police brutality (Box 2)
  - Post-war race relations (Box 2)
  - Progressive Citizens of America (Box 2)
  - Retirement (Box 2)
  - Rogers, Stephen (Box 2)
  - Rosenberg/Sobell case, 1952-1983; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Schwartzman, Marshall (Box 3)
  - Seidenberg, Robert
    See also National Organization for Women
  - Skills for Action (Box 3)
  - Smith, Howard K. (Box 3)
  - Sobell, Helen (Box 3)
    See also Rosenberg/Sobell case
  - Society for Ethical Culture (Box 3)
  - Speaking engagements, 1962-1986 (Box 3)
  - State Press (Little Rock, AR) (Box 3)
  - Syracuse (NY) Citizens’ Committee for Fair and Effective Price Control (Box 3)
  - Syracuse (NY) City School District (Box 3)
  - Syracuse Coalition for the Free Flow of Information in the Broadcast Media (Box 3)
  - Syracuse Developmental Center Advisory Board, See Syracuse State School Advisory Board
  - Syracuse Housing Authority (Box 3)
  - Syracuse Peace Council (Box 3)
  - Syracuse State School Advisory Board (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University Alumni News (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University Center on Human Policy (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University Humanistic Studies Center (Box 3)
  - Syracuse (NY) Women for Peace (Box 3)
  - Thresholds Correctional Solutions (Box 3)
  - Union for Democratic Action, See Americans for Democratic Action
  - United Nations Association of Central New York (Box 3)
  - United States Central Intelligence Agency (Box 3)
  - United States Department of Agriculture Emergency Food Program (Box 3)
  - United States Federal Bureau of Investigation (Box 3)
  - United States Office of Price Administration National Consumer Advisory Committee (Box 3)
  - United States Post Office Department (Box 3)
  - Walsh, William F. (Box 3)
  - War tax resistance (Box 3)
  - Westcott Youth Organization (Syracuse, NY) (Box 3)
  - Women in politics (Box 3)
  - Women’s issues (Box 3)
  - Women’s International League for Peace and Freedom, 1961-1985; undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Young Progressives of America, Syracuse University Chapter (Box 3)
  - Youth March for Integrated Schools, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Zimmer, Melvin N. (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Advocate 3/9/1974 - typescript (Box 4)
  - Books
    - Gutsy Lady Lillian Reiner Book Fund Syracuse, NY, 1991 (Box 4)
    - "That Gutsy Lady" (working title)
      - Manuscript
        - Lillian Reiner’s first draft – typescript, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Jean Hoefer’s draft copy – typescript, 11 folders (Box 4)
      - Research notes
        - "Activities" (Box 4)
        - "Anti-Jew/Black" (Box 4)
        - "Barry Park" (Box 4)
        - "Biographical" (Box 4)
        - "Black rights" (Box 4)
        - "Chapter one" (Box 4)
        - "Brooks, Rodney" (Box 4)
        - "C.O.R.E." (Box 4)
        - "Chronology" (Box 4)
        - "Communist Party" (Box 4)
        - "Cub Scouts" (Box 4)
        - "Death penalty" (Box 4)
        - "DeCrow interview" (Box 4)
        - "Eightieth birthday" (Box 4)
        - "Environmental hazards" (Box 4)
        - "F.B.I." (Box 4)
        - "Family" (Box 4)
        - "Famous people" (Box 4)
        - "Feiner case" (Box 4)
        - "Feminist" (Box 4)
        - "Foster Grandparents" (Box 4)
        - "Friends" (Box 4)
        - Interviews (transcripts)
          - Reiner, Larry, "tape 4a", undated (Box 4)
          - Reiner, Lillian "tape 1", Nov. 15, 1977 (Box 4)
          - Reiner, Lillian "Session2 tape1", Nov. 29, 1977 (Box 4)
          - Reiner, Lillian, 1981; 2 folders (Box 4)
          - Reiner, Lillian "Session 1 tape 2", undated (Box 4)
          - Reiner, Lillian "Interviewer’s notes", undated (Box 4)
          - Washington, Henry, Oct. 26, 1978 (Box 4)
        - "Letters to publishers" (Box 4)
        - "Liberal Party" (Box 4)
        - "Military draft" (Box 4)
        - "N.A.A.C.P." (Box 4)
        - "Newspapers" (Box 4)
        - "Obits" (Box 4)
        - "Outlines" (Box 4)
        - "P.C.A.-A.L.P." (Box 4)
        - "Peace" (Box 4)
        - "Personal philosophy" (Box 4)
        - "Picketing" (Box 4)
        - "Police brutality" (Box 4)
        - "Regal Restaurant" (Box 4)
        - "Reiner’s notes" (Box 4)
        - "Rosenberg/Sobell" (Box 4)
        - "Running for office" (Box 4)
        - "Seidenberg interviews" (Box 4)
        - "Statement of hours and expenses" (Box 4)
        - "Syracuse Peace Council" (Box 4)
        - "United Nations Association" (Box 4)
        - "Wallace campaign" (Box 4)
        - "Yiddish" (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Class notes
    - "Experiences at C.C. School, July 12, 13, 14, 1972" (Box 4)
    - "Family Living and Child Development", Summer 1953 (Box 4)
    - "Home Nursing and Community Health #30", Fall 1953-54 (Box 4)
    - "Social Organization and Deviant Groups", Spring 1954 (Box 4)
    - Sociology 109 "Primary Interaction and Personal Behavior", Spring 1964 (Box 4)
    - Sociology 133 "The Family", Fall 1953 (Box 4)
    - Sociology 142, Spring 1954 (Box 4)
    - Sociology 145 "Leisure and Social Group Work", Spring 1954 (Box 4)
    - Sociology 152b "Leisure and Social Group Work", Spring 1954 (Box 4)
    - Sociology 154a "Child in the Group", Fall 1953-54 (Box 4)
    - Special Ed 141 "Education of Children with Retarded Intelligence", Summer 1954 (Box 4)
  - Journal
    - "10/8 and 11/4, 1962" (Box 4)
    - "August 6-19, 1984" (Box 4)
  - Letters to editors, 1946-1987; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Letters to elected officials, 1946; 1976 (Box 4)
  - Radio scripts "Comment" WSOQ Radio North Syracuse, NY, 1962 (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Academic records, 1953-1972 (Box 5)
  - Appointment calendar, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Artwork
    - Portraits of Lillian Reiner, 2, unframed (Box 5)
    - Paintings by Isabell M. Williams, 3, framed (Box 5)
    - Tribute "The Ballad of Lillian Reiner (framed) (Box 5)
  - Audio recordings
    - Cassette tapes, 30 tapes (Box 5)
    - Vinyl phonograph records, 6 records (Box 5)
  - Awards and certificates
    - 1975-1987, undated (Box 5)
    - Brass bell inscribed "To Lillian Reiner for Outstanding Service on Behalf of Mental Health Jan. 17, 1985 M.H.A.O.C." (Box 8)
    - Plaque inscribed "Gay Light Person of the Year", 1976 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Ceramic vase (Box 8)
      - Cloth with embroidered signatures (Box 8)
      - Lists of addresses and other unidentified notes, 1 folder (Box 8)
      - Political and campaign buttons (Box 8)
  - Clippings
    - 1948-1949 (Box 6)
    - 1953 (Box 6)
    - 1954 (Box 6)
    - 1962 (Box 6)
    - 1971-1984 (Box 6)
    - About Lillian Reiner (Box 6)
  - Employment records, 1955-1974 (Box 6)
  - Financial records, 1971-1976; undated (Box 6)
  - Medical records, 1954-1974 (Box 6)
  - Photographs
    - c. 1890-1987, undated, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Printed material
    - American Friends Service Committee "Steps to Peace", 1951 (Box 7)
    - Association For Childhood Education International "Nursery School Portfolio", 1953 (Box 7)
    - Auerbach, Aline B. "How to Give Your Child a Good Start", 1951 (Box 7)
    - Braden, Anne "House Un-American Activities Committee: Bulwark of Segregation", 1964 (Box 7)
    - Civil Rights Congress "Voices for Freedom", 1951; 4 copies (Box 7)
    - Dawn Bible Students Association "Armageddon Then World Peace", 1960 (Box 7)
    - New York State American Labor Party Council on Public Affairs "A Program for Jobs in N.Y. State", 1954; 7 copies (Box 7)
    - New York State Commission Against Discrimination "Inside Facts", 1952 (Box 7)
    - New York State Department of Commerce Business Program for Women "A Business of Her Own", 1945 (Box 7)
    - Onondaga Community College "A History of the Black Community of Syracuse", 1980 (Box 7)
    - Robins, Raymond "An American Prophet Speaks", 1933; 4 copies (Box 7)
    - Stover, Fred "The Contest between the People and the Plunderers", undated; 6 copies (Box 7)
    - Syracuse Hebrew Day School, "Guidebook to the Syracuse Jewish Community Passover 5734/1974"
    - Town Hall, Inc. "Town Meeting"
      - v. 14 nos. 3, 12, 23, 27, 31-52 (Box 7)
      - v. 15 nos. 1- 16, 19 – 21 (Box 7)
    - Wexley, John "The Judgment of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg", 1955 (Box 7)
    - Wolf, Anna W.M. "What Makes a Good Home?", 1951 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks
    - "Testimonial dinner in honor of Lillian Reiner", Feb. 18, 1956 (Box 7)
    - Eightieth birthday, May 16, 1981 (Box 7)